XMLPatterns.com

Home

Introduction

Patterns

Books

Links

About

Vegas Freebie!
Free Things to do In Las Vegas
www.vegasfreebie.com

|

XMLPatterns.com Information

Develop effective XML documents using structural design patterns.

Contacts

Please feel free to send email using the links below:

Comments about the website: webmaster@xmlpatterns.com

Comments about the patterns: patterns@xmlpatterns.com

General comments and inquiries, advertising information: info@xmlpatterns.com

What They Are Saying About Us

"A very interesting approach to designing/developing XML documents. I would say that it is a must-read for any serious XML developer, not to mention a very interesting concept!!!!!" (XMLPitstop)

"XMLPatterns has really helped me get a handle on the conceptual structure of data" Derrick Bell (Secrets of the XML developer elite)

"I recently came across an oustanding reference site on design patterns for creating good XML. The site is XMLPatterns.com. The content has already been very helpful to me and I recommend this as a useful reference link." (CSharpener's Weblog)

Privacy Statement

Our basic privacy policy is simple. We will not rent, sell, or share personal information that we collect about you.

At XMLPatterns.com, we recognize that privacy of your personal information is important. Here is information on what types of personal information we receive and collect when you use and visit XMLPatterns.com, and how we safeguard your information. We never sell your personal information to third parties.

Log Files

As with most other websites, we collect and use the data contained in log files. The information in the log files include your IP (internet protocol) address, your ISP (internet service provider, such as AOL or Shaw Cable), the browser you used to visit our site (such as Internet Explorer or Firefox), the time you visited our site and which pages you visited throughout our site.

Cookies and Web Beacons

We do use cookies to store information, such as your personal preferences when you visit our site. This could include only showing you a popup once in your visit, or the ability to login to some of our features, such as forums.

We also use third party advertisements on XMLPatterns.com to support our site. Some of these advertisers may use technology such as cookies and web beacons when they advertise on our site, which will also send these advertisers (such as Google through the Google AdSense program) information including your IP address, your ISP , the browser you used to visit our site, and in some cases, whether you have Flash installed. This is generally used for geotargeting purposes (showing New York real estate ads to someone in New York, for example) or showing certain ads based on specific sites visited (such as showing cooking ads to someone who frequents cooking sites).

DoubleClick DART cookies

We also may use DART cookings for ad serving through Google's DoubleClick, which places a cookie on your computer when you are browsing the web and visit a site using DoubleClick advertising (including some Google AdSense advertisements). This cookie is used to serve ads specific to you and your interests ("interest based targeting"). The ads served will be targeted based on your previous browsing history (For example, if you have been viewing sites about visiting Las Vegas, you may see Las Vegas hotel advertisements when viewing a non-related site, such as on a site about hockey). DART uses "non personally identifiable information". It does NOT track personal information about you, such as your name, email address, physical address, telephone number, social security numbers, bank account numbers or credit card numbers. You can opt-out of this ad serving on all sites using this advertising by visiting http://www.doubleclick.com/privacy/dart_adserving.aspx

You can chose to disable or selectively turn off our cookies or third-party cookies in your browser settings, or by managing preferences in programs such as Norton Internet Security. However, this can affect how you are able to interact with our site as well as other websites. This could include the inability to login to services or programs, such as logging into forums or accounts.

Deleting cookies does not mean you are permanently opted out of any advertising program. Unless you have settings that disallow cookies, the next time you visit a site running the advertisements, a new cookie will be added.

We have relationships with other companies that we allow to place ads on our Web pages. As a result of your visit to our site, ad server companies may collect information such as your domain type, your IP address and clickstream information and may be placing and reading cookies on your browser. If you wish to disable cookies, you may do so through your browser options.

Copyright

This website Copyright © 2000-2000 Toivo Lainevool. All rights reserved.

|

XMLPatterns.com

Choice Reducing Container

Abstract

When creating large DTDs, authors are required to learn a large number of attributes and elements, and where they can be positioned in order to know how to use the DTD. By reducing the number of choices that the author has to make at any point in the DTD by group related elements beneath newly introduced elements, the learning requirements of the author can be reduced.

Problem

In a complex DTD with many elements and attributes, a user of a document can be overwhelmed with the number of choices that have to be made. With many options users have a difficult time knowing all of the elements available and the order that these appear in.

Context

In large, general-purpose DTDs where many logical units are presented, and the documents are expected to be authored by humans.

Forces

When the underlying order of the data to be represented, or to make DTDs applicable in many situations, large numbers of logical units need to appear in the DTD. However, presenting large numbers of attributes and elements makes the DTD more difficult to learn by authors of documents.

Solution

Present only a limited number of choices to the author at any point within the document. If the author has the choice of insert 100 different elements at some point in the document, it can be difficult to know how to proceed. By grouping elements into related sets, the number choices to be made at any one point can be reduced. The author has to choose between only a few higher level groups instead of many more detailed elements.

Examples

Here is a DTD that presents several choices to the author:

        

<!ELEMENT Doc
( Para
| OrderedList
| UnorderedList
| Figure
| Artwork )+>

        
      

The author here is present with a choice of 5 different elements to choose from after creating the Doc element. This choice could be limited by introducing new elements and grouping some of the existing elements together as children of the new elements like this:

        

<!ELEMENT Doc (Para | List | Illustration )+)>
<!ELEMENT List (OrderedList | UnorderedList )>
<!ELEMENT Illustration (Figure | Artwork )>

        
      

Discussion

Once the Choice Reducing Pattern is applied, the learning requirements placed on the author of documents is reduced. Application of this pattern can however lead to an increase in the overall number of element types in the DTD. The number of elements in the above example went from 6 to 8 when the Group Choice pattern was applied. This can make the overall complexity of the DTD higher. It can also increase the size of documents.

The Choice Reducing Pattern hides choices from the authors of documents by introducing new elements that hide the details of a piece of the document that the author might not care about at that point in time. By introducing a single higher level element, the number of choices the author needs to make is lower, thereby reducing the learning requirements of the author.

Related Patterns

This Choice Reducing Container is similar to the

Optional Container Element

in that they both try to make the DTD easier to use by the author by introducing new element types. Existing elements are grouped together as children of the new element. One difference between the two is the context they are used in. The Choice Reducing Container relates elements that are all choices in a content group while the

Optional Container Element

relates optional elements from the content group.

The motivation for the two is also different. In the Choice Reducing Container, the amount of information at any one point is reduced, but it is not intended to reduce the overall complexity of the document for a single author. The

Optional Container Element

hides parts of the structure permanently from the view of individual authors. It is likely that some authors will never use certain parts of large DTDs.

Known Uses

References

See

Structuring XML Documents

, Section 4.2.1 - Limiting Choices.

XMLPatterns.com

Collection Element

Abstract

Create a new element whose content model allows only instances of a single element type.

Problem

There is an element that needs to be repeated several times at the same level of a documents.

Context

Multiple elements of the same element type need to appear in the document as siblings of each other. Often metadata about the container needs to be expressed as well. The Collection Element is a logical place to put this metadata. Sometimes, the elements need to be grouped into different categories. Multiple Collection Elements can appear in the document, with each container having elements from one of the sub categories.

Forces

Groups of identical repeated elements often need some context established so that metadata can be associated with the entire group, or to distinguish between different groups of similar elements.

Solution

Create a new element type that contains the multiple elements of the same type. The Collection Element is often named by putting a descriptive ending on the contained element name. For example, a Collection Element of authors might be called AuthorList or AuthorGroup. Another way of naming the Collection Element is to pluralize the contained element name. For example, a collection of Stock elements would be named Stocks.

Examples

Simple Collection Element

          

<Portfolio>
<StockList>
<Stock>
<Name>IBM</Name>
<Price>110.25</Price>
</Stock>
<Stock>
<Name>MSFT</Name>
<Price>89.50</Price>
</Stock>
</StockList>
<Bonds>
...
</Bonds>
</Portfolio>

          
        

Container Element With Metadata

          

<KitchenInventory>
<GlassList location="cupboard3">
<Glass type="shot" number="5"/>
<Glass type="highball" number="8"/>
</GlassList>
<MugList>
...
</MugList>
</KitchenInventory>

          
        

Multiple Categories of Same Collection

          

<Portfolio>
<StockList Exchange="NYSE">
<Stock>
<Name>IBM</Name>
<Price>110.25</Price>
</Stock>
</StockList>
<StockList Exchange="NASDAQ">
<Stock>
<Name>MSFT</Name>
<Price>89.50</Price>
</Stock>
<Stock>
<Name>AMZN</Name>
<Price>80.75</Price>
</Stock>
</StockList>
</Portfolio>

          
        

In this example the Collection Element was needed to establish a context for the exchange data. Without a collection element, this information would have to be duplicated in every Stock element.

Discussion

The resulting structure is often easier to read and process. It does however result in documents that take up more space.

Providing a parent element for a list of elements of the same type allows for the collection to have a context, making it easier to add metadata if needed. This may also make processing and reading the document easier.

If there is a significant metadata for the container, in terms of amount of structure or volume, a

Head-Body

would be appropriate to include inside of the Collection Element.

Related Patterns

This is a specialization of the

Container Element

pattern.

Known Uses

The

DocBook

(http://docbook.org/xml/index.html) DTD has a OrderedList Element, whose only sub-children can be one or more ListItem elements.

XMLPatterns.com

Common Attributes

Abstract

Provide a set of attributes that can be placed on all, or most, elements in the document type.

Problem

There are properties that belong to every element in the document. These properties need to be presented to the document author in an understandable way.

Context

This is a widely applicable pattern and can be used anywhere that a large number of elements need the same attributes applied. It is a common technique for attributes such as IDs, security, and roles.

Forces

The usability of the document type depends a lot on consistency, and this pattern can be used to add consistency.

Solution

Create a common set of attributes that will be used by all or most of the elements in the document type.

Examples

Common Attributes in DTDs

This examples shows a DTD that has two common attributes, id and role, on its all of its elements. The common attribute definition is placed in a parameter entity which is referenced by all of the ATTLIST definitions.

            

<!ENTITY % common.att
'id   ID      #IMPLIED
role NMTOKEN #IMPLIED'>

<!ELEMENT Person (FirstName, LastName)>
<!ATTLIST Person %common.att;>

<!ELEMENT FirstName (#PCDATA)>
<!ATTLIST FirstName %common.att;>

<!ELEMENT LastName (#PCDATA)>
<!ATTLIST LastName %common.att;>

            
          

Common Attributes in XML Schemas

This example shows how to implement the same document structure as the above examples using the

XSL Schema language Attributes Groups

(http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-0/#AttrGroups) .

          

<?xml version="1.0"?>
<schema xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/XMLSchema"
targetNamespace="http://www.xmlpatterns.com/XMLSchema-fragment"
xmlns:xsf="http://www.xmlpatterns.com/XMLSchema-fragment">

<attributeGroup name="CommonAtts">
<attribute name="id" type="ID"/>
<attribute name="role" type="NMTOKEN"/>
</attributeGroup>

<complexType name="NameType">
<attributeGroup ref="CommonAtts"/>
</complexType>

<complexType name="PersonType" content="elementOnly">
<element name="FirstName" type="xsf:NameType"/>
<element name="LastName" type="xsf:NameType"/>
<attributeGroup ref="CommonAtts"/>
</complexType>

<element name="Person" type="xsf:PersonType"/>

</schema>

          
        

Discussion

Global attributes often add many choices at any point in the document. Users have more selections available to them, and this could complicate authoring, however, some of the complexity that adding attributes to every element brings is lessened if these attributes are applied consistently. If users can expect the same common attribute on every element, it does not take a lot of extra effort to process the information. It will be easier to author or process a document that has a consistently applied set of common attributes on all elements compared to one that has inconsistently applied attributes on most of the elements.

An ID attribute is a typical use for a common attribute. It is useful to be able to reference any element in the document using this.

Related Patterns

The common attributes are usually declared in a

Flyweight

to help maintainability.

Known Uses

The

XMLspec DTD Common Attributes Chapter

(http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/06/xmlspec-report-v21.htm#cmnatts) explains the use of common attributes in the DTD.

XHTML defines a set of core attributes. These attributes are applied to almost every element in the XHTML document type. The core attributes are defined like this:

          

<!ENTITY % coreattrs
"id     ID           #IMPLIED
class  CDATA        #IMPLIED
style  %StyleSheet; #IMPLIED
title  %Text;       #IMPLIED"
>

          
        

Even the simple line break element has these attributes added to it:

          

<!ELEMENT br EMPTY>  <!-- forced line break -->
<!ATTLIST br
%coreattrs;
>

          
        

References

See

Structuring XML Documents

, Section 3.2.4: Global Attributes. Thanks to

Hans C. Arents

for supplying the correct XSL Schema definition used in the pattern.

XMLPatterns.com

Consistent Element Set

Abstract

Provide a set of elements which is consistently grouped together as the content models of a number of other elements.

Problem

Providing a flexible DTD structure could require authors to learn which element types can be used in content models of a variety of other element types. Having different content models for every element makes it difficult to authors to learn a DTD, and could make processing software more complex.

Context

Anywhere where a large number of elements can be sub elements of many different parent element types.

Forces

Large number of elements are difficult to use effectively. They can be difficult to learn and process.

Solution

Where sub elements appear, consistently provide the same set of elements in many different places. This reduces the learning requirements of authors. Usually the element set is defined with an entity parameter, and the entity parameter is referred to from each place the set needs to appear.

Examples

A DTD with inconsistent sets of elements in content model of various elements are difficult to learn how to use. For example:

        

<!ELEMENT Foo (A|B|C|E)*>
<!ELEMENT Bar (A|B|C|D)*>
<!ELEMENT Baz (A|C|D|E)*>

        
      

The next DTD is much easier to learn how to use, but some compromises must be made. It is often better to introduce consistency for the sake of ease-of-use.

        

<!ENTITY % content "A|B|C|D|E">
<!ELEMENT Foo (%content;)*>
<!ELEMENT Bar (%content;)*>
<!ELEMENT Baz (%content;)*>

        
      

Here the author has more flexibility, but there is more consistency. This can make it easier for processing software as well.

Discussion

The resulting structure provides easier to learn, consistent sets of elements. Providing consistent sets of elements is far easier for authors to learn. Some compromises might need to be made in the details of the structure to provide this consistency, but this is usually worth the price.

Related Patterns

Known Uses

In XHTML, there are element sets for block content, and inline content. The block content element set is used for all content that can be used at the paragraph level. Inline content is used consistently within paragraphs.

XMLPatterns.com

Content Type Label

Abstract

Parameter entities are created to represent different types of values within a DTD.

Problem

DTDs provide limited type information for content of attributes and elements. Type information is often useful to have in a language.

Context

Any time DTDs are used and it is useful to convey type information.

Forces

Expressing type information helps in creating understandable and maintainable DTDs.

Solution

Create parameter entities to represent different data types. These parameters can be used in attribute and element content descriptions.

Examples

The following DTD fragment is taken from a payroll system. The first line defines a parameter entity to represent a employee number type. In each place in the DTD where a employee number is needed as content, this parameter entity is used.

        

<!ENTITY % EmployeeNum "NMTOKEN">

<!ELEMENT Order (LineItem*)>

<!ELEMENT Employee (Name, Address)>
<!ATTLIST Employee Number %EmployeeNum;>

<!ELEMENT PayRecord (Period, Hours)>
<!ATTLIST PayRecord Employee %EmployeeNum;>

        
      

Discussion

This pattern does not change the structure or constraints of the documents that are instances of the DTD, but it does make the DTD easier to understand and maintain.

This pattern increases understandability of the DTD by documenting the intended use of the content types to readers of the DTD. Looking at the above example we can see that it becomes obvious that the Employee's Number attribute and the PayRecord's Employee attribute contain the same type of value. If they were both just NMTOKENs this may not have been as obvious.

Maintainability of DTDs is increased by allowing all related content types to be changed from a single place. For instance, in the Examples section above if the company this payroll system was created for merges with another company, and the employee numbers from the new company can contain a space, the "NMTOKEN" attribute type is no longer valid. By changing the EmployeeNum parameter entity to "CDATA", all references to the employee number in the DTD can be changed.

Related Patterns

This is an example of a

Flyweight

.

Known Uses

XHTML

(http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/) uses Content Type Labels extensively. For example:

        

<!ENTITY % URI "CDATA">
<!-- a Uniform Resource Identifier, see [RFC2396] -->

<!ENTITY % FrameTarget "NMTOKEN">
<!-- render in this frame -->

<!-- document base URI -->

<!ELEMENT base EMPTY>
<!ATTLIST base
href        %URI;          #IMPLIED
target      %FrameTarget;  #IMPLIED
>

        
      

The above excepts shows how Content Type Labels are used to make it clearer what is expected in the attributes of the base element.

References

The document

XML Modularization of HTML 4.0

(http://www.altheim.com/specs/xhtml/NOTE-xhtml-modular.html#sec2.2.1) by Murray Altheim explains the use of this pattern in XHTML.

XMLPatterns.com

Envelope

Abstract

Provide a document type which is defined to be a holder for other, arbitrary XML data.

Problem

Different sets of data need to be delivered to a system in a consistent way.

Context

This pattern applies when different sets of data need to be used in some system. The structure of the data itself varies, or is not known at the time the system is being built.

Forces

This pattern allows for Flexibility by allowing elements from other documents to be embedded into a consistent holder.

This pattern allows for a separation of concerns between different document types. Mixing issues such as transport with document data is usually not a good idea.

Solution

Create a document type which will act as a holder for the varying set of data.

Examples

This example shows a very simple envelope which consists of sender and a receiver children elements. Note the use of two different namespaces to allow an XML parser to read the document, which contains elements from both the Envelope (envelope.dtd) and the embedded data (my-stuff.dtd)

        

<e:Envelope xmlsns:e="http://xmlpatterns.com/envelope.dtd">
<e:sender name="bob"/>
<e:receiver name="http://xmlpatterns.com/message-receiver.cgi"/>
<myStuff:message xmlsns:e="http://xmlpatterns.com/my-stuff.dtd">
This is my message
</myStuff:message>
</e:Envelope>

        
      

Discussion

The Envelope is used as a delivery mechanism for XML data. Document types created for holding domain data should not be responsible, for defining transport ways to do deal with things such as transport, security, delivery and packaging. The envelope provide for a clear separation between these things and the data itself.

Related Patterns

This is similar to the

Catch-All Element

, except that the the document type of the Envelope pattern exists solely as an holder for other data and, the

Catch-All Element

is for embedding new elements within exsisting data.

Known Uses

SOAP (Simple Object Access Protocol)

(http://www.w3.org/TR/SOAP/) is an Envelope for doing remote transport of messages.

References

XMLPatterns.com

Extensible Content Model

Abstract

Provide a mechanism which allows additional elements to be added into existing content models.

Problem

At the time of designing the document type, the designer may not be able to foresee all of the uses and situations where document instances will be used. To provide for flexibility, the contents of elements can be made to be redefinable by the document instance.

Context

This is a very general mechanism that can be used anytime additional flexibility is needed.

Forces

Flexibility is often required for a document type to be able to be used effectively. Flexibility, however often makes processing of the documents more difficult. Customization of software is often needed to deal with the flexibility.

Solution

The designer of the document can add a mechanism to allow the author of a document instance to extend an element definition from the document type.

Examples

Using DTDs

This example uses a DTD that allows the document instance to extend an Address element. This is done through use a parameter entity which is defined in the DTD, but the creator of the document instance can overwrite.

First a DTD is created that defines a simple Address type, consisting only of the Name, Street and City. Realizing that this may not be enough for all users of this document type, the designer defines a parameter entity called local.address that is blank ("") but can be extended in the document instance.

purchase_order.dtd

            

<!ENTITY % local.address "">
<!ENTITY % address "Name, Street, City %local.address;">
<!ELEMENT PurchaseOrder ( Item, ShipTo, BillTo )>
<!ELEMENT Item   (#PCDATA)>
<!ELEMENT ShipTo (%address;)>;
<!ELEMENT BillTo (%address;)>;
<!ELEMENT Name   (#PCDATA)>
<!ELEMENT Street (#PCDATA)>
<!ELEMENT City   (#PCDATA)>

            
          

The creator of a document decides that the address defined in the DTD is inadequate for the document being create, so he extends the definition of an Address to include State and Zip. To do this he creates his own definition of the local.address Parameter Entity. This allows him to add these elements to his own address structure.

mydoc.xml

            

<!DOCTYPE PURCHASE_ORDER SYSTEM "purchase_order.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % local.address ", State, Zip" >
<!ELEMENT State (#PCDATA)>
<!ELEMENT Zip (#PCDATA)>
]>
<PurchaseOrder>
<Item>X123</Item>
<ShipTo>
<Name>Bob Smith</Name>
<Street>123 Maple Dr.</Street>
<City>Anytown</City>
<State>CA</State>
<Zip>12345</Zip>
</ShipTo>
<BillTo>
<Name>Bob Smith</Name>
<Street>123 Maple Dr.</Street>
<City>Anytown</City>
<State>CA</State>
<Zip>12345</Zip>
</BillTo>
</PurchaseOrder>

            
          

Using XML Schemas

This next example uses XML Schemas to do the same thing. We use the XML Schema mechanism of deriving types by extension to do this. This example is based on a working draft of the XML Schema proposal, so this example may not be compatible with future versions of the XML Schema. A schema is created to include the simple Address type with a Name, Street, and City.

PurchaseOrder.xsd

            

<xsd:schema
xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/1999/XMLSchema">

<xsd:element
name="purchaseOrder"
type="PurchaseOrderType"/>
<xsd:complexType name="PurchaseOrderType">
<xsd:element name="Item"   type="xsd:string"/>
<xsd:element name="ShipTo" type="Address"/>
<xsd:element name="BillTo" type="Address"/>
</xsd:complexType>

<xsd:complexType name="Address">
<xsd:element name="Name"   type="xsd:string"/>
<xsd:element name="Street" type="xsd:string"/>
<xsd:element name="City"   type="xsd:string"/>
</xsd:complexType>

</xsd:schema>

            
          

The author of a document realizes that this simple address definition will not be adequate, so a new address type is created. The new type is extended from the old type, and adds the State and Zip elements.

US-Address.xsd

            

<xsd:schema
xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/1999/XMLSchema"
xmlns:po="http:www.xmlpatterns.com/PurchaseOrder">

<xsd:complexType name="US-Address"
base="po:Address"
derivedBy="extension">
<xsd:element name="State"  type="xsd:string"/>
<xsd:element name="Zip"    type="xsd:decimal"/>
</xsd:complexType>

</xsd:schema>

            
          

To use the new address type in a document instance, both of the schema files are used.

mydoc.xml

            

<PurchaseOrder
xmlns="http:www.xmlpatterns.com/PurchaseOrder"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/1999/XMLSchema-instance"
xmlns:us="http://www.xmlpatterns.com/US-Address"
xsi:schemaLocation=
"http://www.xmlpatterns.com/purchaseOrder.xsd
http://www.xmlpatterns.com/US-Address.xsd">

<Item>X123</Item>
<ShipTo xsi:type="us:US-Address">
<Name>Bob Smith</Name>
<Street>123 Maple Dr.</Street>
<City>Anytown</City>
<State>CA</State>
<Zip>12345</Zip>
</ShipTo>
<BillTo xsi:type="us:US-Address">
<Name>Bob Smith</Name>
<Street>123 Maple Dr.</Street>
<City>Anytown</City>
<State>CA</State>
<Zip>12345</Zip>
</BillTo>
</PurchaseOrder>

            
          

Discussion

This provides a powerful extension mechanism to the authors of documents. Like with all added flexibility, the power comes with a price. Extensible Content Models create new element types that standard processing tools for a document type would not be able to process correctly. Often customization of software is needed to handle the extensions correctly.

This technique has the advantage of not needlessly over complicating the structure of the document type if the flexibility is not needed. Authors can use the document type without even being aware that the extension mechanism exists. The existence of these Extensible Content Models can be made known only to "power users", if desired.

Related Patterns

This mechanism is powerful, but also requires knowledge of DTD syntax to apply. Often the

Generic Element

pattern combined with

Role Attribute

s may be a more appropriate choice if the authors of the document are not experienced with XML.

Known Uses

The

Information and Content Exchange (ICE) Protocol Appendix A

(http://www.icestandard.org/servlet/RetrievePage?site=ice&page=current_specs) demonstrates applications of this pattern.

The

XMLspec DTD

(http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/06/xmlspec-report-v21.htm#AEN258) uses parameter entities to allow for customization of many elements.

The DocBook DTD allows for the types of

customizations

(http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/intro.html) .

References

See

Structuring XML Documents

, Section 8.1.2: Adding Elements Types to a DTD.

XMLPatterns.com

Head-Body

Abstract

When a large amount of metadata needs to be included in an element the designer may create two children for the element, one for the metadata and one for the body of the document.

Problem

Sometimes, an element has a large amount of metadata, and this metadata may need to be structured. In common XML usage, attributes are used for metadata. But with a large amount of metadata it is difficult for authors to include this information within attributes, which have limited structure. Including metadata as sibling elements of content elements leads to the potential to confuse the metadata and the data meant to be in the body of the element.

Context

There is a large amount of metadata about some piece of content. For example information about the title, creation date, and authors of a document should be included with the document, but this is not really information that belong in the body of the document.

Forces

A clear separation is needed between what is metadata and what is data that forms the body of the document. This affects ease of authoring and processing of the document because the context of the data is implied. The metadata needed for an element needs to structured in such a way that attributes are difficult to use.

Solution

Create head and body elements. The element that contains the head and body elements can be referred to as the skeleton element. The metadata for the document goes into the head element, and the data for the document itself goes into the body element. The XML takes the following form:

        

<Skeleton>
<Head>
... meta information ...
</Head>
<Body>
... body of document ...
</Body>
</Skeletion>

        
      

Examples

        

<Document>
<Head>
<Author>John Doe</Author>
<Author>Frank Black</Author>
<CreationDate>June 16, 1999</CreationDate>
</Head>
<Body>
This is a document.
</Body>
</Document>

        
      

In this case, the skeleton element is the document root, and the metadata is structured information about the authors of the document and the creation date of the document. The Head-Body pattern is often used at the document level, but it can also be used at levels deeper within a document. For example the pattern could be used inside of a Table element like this:

        

<Document>
<Table>
<TableHead>
<Title>
A <Italic>Sample<Italic> Table
</Title>
</TableHead>
<TableBody>
<Row>Row 1</Row>
<Row>Row 2</Row>
</TableBody>
</Table>
</Document>

        
      

In this case the skeleton element is a table, which needs structure for its Title data.

Discussion

Two new elements are introduced which distinguish the metadata from the body of the document. This gives processing software context to distinguish these two types of data.

Because this introduced two additional elements, the resulting documents are larger than they would be without the application of this pattern

The resulting documents are often easier to understand because of the clear separation of metadata and the document body itself. The metadata is in the Head element and the document itself goes in the Body element. Authors and processing software can clearly distinguish the context of the data they are using.

Documents are also often easier to process because they allow metadata to be structured, unlike if attributes were use for the metadata of the document.

For an interesting alternative, see Don Park's "Neck" pattern (http://www.docuverse.com/blog/donpark/EntryViewPage.aspx?guid=831)

Related Patterns

The Head-Body Pattern consists of two new

Container Element

s added to the structure of the document, one for the Head element, and one for the Body. This is a specialization of the

Separate Metadata and Data

.

Known Uses

HEAD and BODY elements in XHTML.

SOAP (Simple Object Access Protocol)

(http://www.w3.org/TR/SOAP/) uses Header and Body Elements inside an Envelope element.

References

Rick Jelliffe discusses this in a chapter entitled "The Document Shell" in:

The XML & SGML Cookbook: Recipes for Structured Information

XMLPatterns.com

Metadata in Separate Document

Abstract

When there is a large amount of metadata for a document it can make sense to separate this into a different document altogether, with its own document type.

Problem

There may a large amount of metadata for a document. If much of this data is required, it could make the document difficult to author and read.

Context

There is a large amount of metadata to be associated with the documents. If the metadata for several documents is the same.

Forces

Metadata can add complexity to a document, making it more difficult to author a document. When processing documents, the metadata may not be needed by some programs. Having the metadata in the document can increase processing time.

Solution

Place the metadata in the separate document. This document should have its own document type. There is a link placed in the document that refers to the metadata document.

If the metadata for several documents is the same, this can be a very good pattern to use. If, for example, a document requires extensive biographical information about its authors, and several of the documents are by the same author, the single metadata document can be used to minimize replication and ease maintenance.

External parsed entities parsed entities can be used in a similar way, but the document type of the original document does not get simplified.

Examples

Here is an example that references author information from an external file.

File: author-info.xml

        

<Author>
<Name>Robert Smith</Name>
<BirthDate>21-04-1960</BirthDate>
<Address>123 Maple Street</Address>
</Author>

        
      

File: document.xml

        

<!DOCTYPE DOCUMENT[
<!ENTITY author-info SYSTEM "author-info.xml">
]>
<Document>
<Head>
&author-info;
</Head>
<Body>
This is the document.
</Body>
</Document>

        
      

Discussion

This pattern makes the separation between the data and the metadata very clear, very little confusion can be made between the data and metadata.

The metadata and data can be defined at different times in the development cycle, allowing for iterative development, or for different authors to work on the data and metadata at the same time.

By having the metadata in a separate document, many documents can include the metadata from the same source. In the Example above, if the address of the author had changed, all of the documents which included this document would be automatically changed as well.

Related Patterns

This is a specialization of both the the

Separate Metadata and Data

and patterns.

Known Uses

References

See:

The XML & SGML Cookbook

page 2-23.

XMLPatterns.com

Multiple Document Types

Abstract

When a system needs to represent a range of different document types, each document type can be represented by a completely separate declarations.

Problem

A system needs to represent different types of information. This information may be used at different times, or may be used by different parts of the system.

Context

Systems which need to represent a variety of information at different times or places.

Forces

Processing and authoring of documents can be simplified if different document types are used to represent different sets of data.

Solution

Use different document types to represent different sets of data within the system.

Examples

In a payroll system, data about the Employees, and data about the hours they work can be represented by separate documents.

Employees.dtd:

        

<!ELEMENT Employee (Name, HourlyRate)>
<!ATTLIST Employee id ID #REQUIRED>

<!ELEMENT Name (#PCDATA)>

<!ELEMENT HourlyRate (#PCDATA)>

        
      

HoursWorked.dtd:

        

<!ELEMENT PayPeriod (Employee+)>
<!ATTLIST PayPeriod
StartDate #CDATA
EndDate   #CDATA>

<!ELEMENT Employee (HoursWorked)>
<!ATTLIST Employee id NMTOKEN>

<!ELEMENT HoursWorked (#PCDATA)>

        
      

Discussion

If different people will authoring the different types of documents it is a good idea to have completely separate document types, because authors will not need to be exposed to parts of the document types that are not needed.

Having separate document types allows the different DTDs to be versioned independently.

Related Patterns

Universal Root

allows multiple types of data under one document root.

Multi Root Document Types

allows for multiple types of documents to be declared in a single declaration.

Known Uses

XMLPatterns.com

Multi Root Document Types

Abstract

A single document type with multiple root elements is used to handle varying documents that may exist within a system.

Problem

A system needs to handle varying types of documents. These are somehow related, yet each type of document needs a unique identity provided by a document root.

Context

Systems where varying types of documents need to be processed, but the different documents are closely related.

Forces

Maintainability of the system is effected by how the document types are organized.

Solution

Create a single declaration with multiple root elements for the different document types.

Examples

The two documents below show two different bank transactions, a deposit and a withdrawal. The document have different root elements, but many other common elements. Both of these documents use the same DTD, but declare different roots.

        

<!DOCTYPE "Deposit" SYSTEM "bank.dtd">
<Deposit>
<Account id="123"/>
<Amount currency="USD">100.00</Amount>
<Date>05-10-2000</Date>
</Deposit>

        
      

        

<!DOCTYPE "Withdrawal" SYSTEM "bank.dtd">
<Withdrawal>
<Account id="123"/>
<Amount currency="USD">100.00</Amount>
<Date>05-10-2000</Date>
</Withdrawal>

        
      

Discussion

Allows the different document types to easily share structure. Having all of the related document types declared in a single file can increase maintainability. However, if revisions need to be made to the different document types separately, it might be better having separate declarations.

Related Patterns

Universal Root

and

Multiple Document Types

are alternatives.

Known Uses

In

DocBook

(http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/) the root element can be a set or a book element.

XMLPatterns.com

Parallel Design

Abstract

Creating structures that for different elements that are very similar to one another makes DTD easier to use and understand.

Problem

Authoring a document with complex structure can be difficult if there are many elements, and each of these elements has their own particular content models.

Context

Any document that is large enough to be potentially difficult to learn.

Forces

Having consistency in the structure of document types makes document instances easier to learn and process.

Solution

For elements that are similar in function use structures that are as close to identical as possible.

Examples

        

<!ELEMENT Figure (Title, FigureBody, Number?)>
<!ATTLIST Figure height CDATA
width  CDATA
id     ID  #REQUIRED>

<!ELEMENT Table (Title, TableBody, Number?)>
<!ATTLIST Table height CDATA
width  CDATA
id     ID  #REQUIRED>

        
      

These two elements "Figure" and "Table" have very similar content and identical attribute lists. This makes it very easy for authors of the document. Once they have learned the structure of one of the elements, the other one will be easy to use. The more variation there is between the two, the easier it is to confuse the two structures.

Discussion

The more consistent the structure of various elements is the easier it is to learn to use a document type. Subtle differences in structure can be particularly difficult to learn. If, for example, in the above example, one of the "id" attributes was IMPLIED and the other one was REQUIRED, this would be a difficult distinction to remember. Users would constantly need to refer to the documentation to remind them which element's id was required and which one wasn't.

Related Patterns

Often the parts of the structure that are the same between two elements can be represented as

Flyweight

s. This will help ensure that the two structures remain similar even through revisions of the document type.

Known Uses

The

DocBook

(http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/intro.html) DTD defines these four entities:

        

<!ENTITY % div.title.content
"title, subtitle?, titleabbrev?">

<!ENTITY % bookcomponent.title.content
"title, subtitle?, titleabbrev?">

<!ENTITY % sect.title.content
"title, subtitle?, titleabbrev?">

<!ENTITY % refsect.title.content
"title, subtitle?, titleabbrev?">

        
      

All four of the elements have identical content model. This helps enormously in learning the specifics of this DTD.

References

See

Structuring XML Documents

, Section 3.2.2.

XMLPatterns.com

Referenced Note

Abstract

When an area in text needs to refer to a note that will be placed in a different part of the document, a reference is made to a separate entity using an IDREF.

Problem

Some text needs to make a reference to another piece of text that is located elsewhere with the original text. This could be a footnote, an annotation, or an endnote. The position of the note in the final document will not be known until the document is rendered.

Context

Notes occur when a comment needs to be made about a piece of text, but the author does not want the main text flow to be interrupted. This is a very publication oriented pattern, it is not as relevant in data interchange documents.

Forces

Ease of Use and Ease of Processing is effected by how a note is organized.

Solution

The note is put in a element which is not contained within the flow of the text where the note is referenced from. An attribute of type ID is put on the note element, and an element is inserted into the flow of the text with an IDREF that refers to the note's ID. A different solution would be to simply use an inline element to include the note as such:

        

<Paragraph>This paragraph refers to a note.
<Note>This is the note.</Note>
</Paragraph>

        
      

This solution has a couple of potential disadvantages:

The note cannot be referred to from more than one place.
The note is not physically removed from the text in the marked up document. It may more difficult for the author of the document to realize how the note will be used in the published form of the document.

Examples

        

<Paragraph>
This paragraph refers to a note.
<NoteReference ref="1"/>
</Paragraph>
<Note id="1">This is the note.</Note>

        
      

When rendered the document could be made to look like this:

        

This paragraph refers to a note.
1
... rest of page ...

1: This is a note.
...end of page

        
      

Discussion

Using this pattern can lead to easier to use documents. Since authors expect notes to be separated from the flow of text, this pattern can lead to more natural mark up.

Rendering software can be simplified if the notes are declared before they will be used. For example if the note is to go on the bottom of a page, the rendering software can calculate page breaks on the fly if the size of the note is already known when the reference to it is encountered.

Related Patterns

This is an example of a

Domain Element

from the publishing world.

Also consider using

Declare Before First Use

with this pattern.

Known Uses

References

This is a generalization of:

Footnote Pattern

(http://www.utoronto.ca/ian/books/xmlbook/Footnote.html) on the The XML Specification Guide web site.

XMLPatterns.com

Separate Metadata and Data

Abstract

When documents contain content and data about the content, the two types of data should be clearly separated.

Problem

A document contains two distinct types of data, the content of the document, and data about the content. The data about the content is referred to as metadata. Since a document contains these two different types of data, it is not always to distinguish between the two types of data. For example:

        

<ArticleSummaries>
<Author>Phred Smith</Author>
<Name>Patterns of Stereo Design</Name>
<Author>J.R. Dolby</Author>
<Summary>
Use of patterns to arrange stereo components.
</Summary>
</ArticleSummary>

        
      

Here there are two instances of the Author element, and at first glance it might not be possible to tell what the first instance of Author represents. Is it the author of the article being summarized? Is it the author of the article itself? It can be difficult to distinguish metadata from data.

Context

Data about the data needs to be included in a document. This could be things like the author's name, the creation date, security levels of the data, namespace information, schema information, or identification attributes for use with cross references.

Forces

A clear separation is needed between what is metadata and what is data that forms the body of the document. This affects ease of authoring and processing of the document because the context of the data is clear.

Solution

The context of the data and the metadata should be made clear. The metadata should usually appear before the data that it describes. This makes it clearer what the metadata is about, and allows processing software to know about the data before it actually gets the data. For example the size of a table might be considered metadata. If the processing software gets the size of the table before the actual data, it can layout the table and then insert t he data in the proper place as it encounters it.

Examples

See the

Metadata in Separate Document

,

Head-Body

patterns for examples.

Discussion

The resulting context provides structures that clearly identify the metadata as metadata. Often this pattern introduces new constructs to the document, so the overall length of the document may be increased. Authors and processing software need to clearly distinguish between metadata and content. This is not always possible to tell from the element names or positions. It is better to provide a context that will disambiguate the types of data. Obviously the first step in using this pattern is to be able to identify the difference between metadata and data. This is not always an easy task.

Related Patterns

Metadata in Separate Document

,

Head-Body

are specializations of this pattern.

Known Uses

The

W3C Namespace Recommendation

(http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml-names/) includes namespace information in attributes that make it clearer that this is data about the documents, and not really part of the document itself.

The XHTML DTD uses Head and Body elements to distinguish the metadata from the data.

XMLPatterns.com

Short Understandable Names

Abstract

Names of elements and attributes should short and understandable by authors and developers of processing software.

Problem

Names need to be given to each attribute and name.

Context

This pattern can be used in any document type. All documents have named elements and attributes.

Forces

Shorter names make the authoring of documents easier and reduces the overall length of documents. Names that are too short make the document difficult to understand.

Solution

Use names that are long enough to convey the meaning of the document to its intended audience, but are short enough to be typed easily. Similar naming length issues are seen in programming languages.

Examples

A element name such as TelephoneDescription is fairly long, PhoneDescription or PhoneDesc might be more appropriate choices.

Discussion

Use well known terms and abbreviations from the domain that the document deals with. These terms and abbreviations should be used consistently throughout the document. The audience of the document must be kept in mind, too much jargon can intimidate novices very quickly.

Context can be take into account to shorten names as well. In the following sample:

          

            <Telephone>
            <TelephoneModelName>X-259</TelephoneModelName>
            </Telephone>

          
        

The element name TelephoneModelName could easily be shortened to ModelName without loosing any understandability of the document.

Related Patterns

Known Uses

HTML uses many element names which are shortened beyond understandability, for example the b, i, dt, and ul elements are very cryptic to novice users. Element names such as font and img convey much more meaning, and are not long enough to cause problems.